Miguel Jiménez

Curriculum Vitae¹

Computer Science Department University of Victoria Victoria, British Columbia, Canada miguel@uvic.ca miguel@migueljimenez.co https://migueljimenez.co

Research Interests

My area of research is Software Engineering with a focus on the design and development of architectures and infrastructures for self-adaptive software systems.

My research interests include self-adaptive systems, continuous software engineering, models at run-time and domain specific languages. I am currently working towards automated software evolution of cloud software applications through quality-driven continuous experimentation.

Education

2016-Present Ph.D. in Computer Science - University of Victoria, Victoria, Canada

GPA 3.85/4

Advised by Hausi Müller and Gabriel Tamura

Thesis topic: Continuous software evolution at run-time

2014-2016 M.Sc. in Software Engineering - Universidad Icesi, Cali, Colombia

GPA 3.87/4

Advised by Gabriel Tamura

Thesis: A framework for generating and deploying dynamic performance monitors for self-

adaptive software systems

2009-2014 B.E. in Systems Engineering - Universidad Icesi, Cali, Colombia

GPA 3.21/4 • Engineering Dean's list in semesters VI, VII, VIII and IX

Advised by Angela Villota-Gomez and Gabriel Tamura

Degree project: PaSCAni: A language for run-time V&V of functional requirements (Spanish)

Selected Awards and Honors

2018, 2019	Travel Scholarship, CRA-URMD Grad Cohort
2017, 2018	UVic Graduate Award, University of Victoria
2017	Howard E. Petch Research Scholarship, University of Victoria
2017, 2018	IBM Advanced Studies Grant, IBM
2016	Doctoral Fellowship (full academic scholarship), University of Victoria
2014	Master's Fellowship (full academic scholarship), Universidad Icesi
2014	Student Loan Forgiveness , Colombian Institute of Educational Credit and Technical Studies
2013	Top ECAES Exam, Colombian Institute for the Promotion of Higher Education
2009	Undergraduate Scholarship (25%), Universidad Icesi
2011-2014	Engineering Dean's list in semesters VI, VII, VIII, & IX, Universidad Icesi

¹This curriculum vitae was last updated on March 31, 2019. Download the latest version from migueljimenez.co/cv.pdf

Publications

Refereed Journal Articles

Refereed Conference Proceedings

Refereed Workshop Proceedings

Selected Posters and Contributed Talks

Research Experience

Jan 2018 - **Project Lead Student**

Present IBM Advanced Studies + Rigi Research Group, University of Victoria, Canada

Advised by Joe Wigglesworth (IBM), Hausi Müller and Gabriel Tamura

Conduct research and collaborate with the team behind IBM Cloud Automation Manager to develop round-trip engineering mechanisms for infrastructure as code, and automate continuous experimentation for deployments on the cloud.

Jan 2014 - Graduate Research Assistant

Aug 2016 i2T/DRISO Research Group, Universidad Icesi, Colombia

Advised by Gabriel Tamura

- Identified challenges in dynamic performance monitoring of self-adaptive systems and proposed technical solutions following the SOA philosophy to advance the state of the art
- Designed and implemented two domain-specific languages for dynamic monitoring and distributed deployment
- Managed the computing resources of the i2T/DRISO research group's computing grid (15 physical machines)

Jun 2013 - Research Assistant Intern

Dec 2013 i2T/DRISO Research Group, Universidad Icesi, Colombia

Advised by Gabriel Tamura

Implemented and conducted quantitative experiments for the matrix multiplication problem.

Teaching and Mentoring Experience

Spring 2018 Graduate Teaching Assistant

Assistance Centre in Computer Science, University of Victoria

Tutored students and assisted them with programming assignments in one-on-one sessions.

2016-2018 Graduate Teaching Assistant

Fundamentals of Programming with Engineering Applications (CSC 111), University of Victoria

Instructor: Hausi Müller

- Lectured weekly labs and assisted students with programming and lab assignments
- Co-led weekly meetings and developed teaching material and quizzes
- Developed GradeBuddy, a program to assist teaching assistants and professors in automating the marking of programming assignments
- Developed a multi-platform installation assistant to ease the installation of CLion and its dependencies on Windows, Mac and Linux
- Developed examgen, a program to generate examinations along with their solutions from a YAML input file. The resulting files are rendered to either MEX or Moodle. By creating examgen, we stopped printing 2800 quizzes and reduced marking time by 30h per term
- Deployed an online platform to host and mark programming assignments

Fall 2016 Graduate Teaching Assistant

Data Structures I (CSC 225), University of Victoria

Instructor: Ulrike Stege

Lectured weekly labs, developed scripts to automate marking and graded assignments.

Spring 2016 Technical Advisor

Undergraduate degree project, Interactive Media Design Program - Universidad Icesi

Knowledge management and dissemination: alternative soccer culture

Student: Juan David Flórez Bautista

Spring 2015 Tutor

Undergraduate degree project, Interactive Media Design Program - Universidad Icesi

Folii: natural and interactive encyclopedia mediated by citizen science

Students: Juan Pablo Pérez, Mauricio Alberto Toro

Spring 2011 *Teaching Assistant*

Data Structures and Algorithms, Universidad Icesi

Instructor: Angela Villota-Gomez Graded programming assignments.

Invited Talks

Service and Volunteering

2011-2012 Volunteer instructor for the Web Programming Club

Universidad Icesi, Cali, Colombia

Developed teaching material and lectured members of the programming club on HTML, CSS and JavaScript.

Skills

Programming Languages

Java, Xtend

JavaScript, CSS, HTML

C Python Go C# Oz

ShellScript

Technical Skills

Architecture Design Build Automation

Containerized Applications
Continuous Delivery
Data mining (basic)
Infrastructure Provision
Language Engineering
Microservices Architecture
Object Oriented Programming

Service Component Architecture

Languages

Spanish (Native) English (Fluent) French (Elementary)

Performance Monitoring